

Linklab (Olsson Hall - Second Floor), University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

□ (434) 466-7628 | \blacksquare sb5ce@virginia.edu | \boxdot soniabaee | \boxdot sonia-baee

Profile

I am a third-year as a Ph.D. student at the University of Virginia in the Department of System and Information Engineering, working with Dr. Laura Barnes. In our research, we use mobile sensing technology, and the associated contextual data (social-media, GPS, Accelerometer, Ecological Momentary Assessment (EMA), and phone usage) in the mental health domain to deliver just-in-time prompts to individuals. We would like to give the right treatment at the right time for each individual. We are planning to use digital coaching to address idiosyncratic physical, behavioral and psychological processes of individual users to optimize utilization, compliance, efficacy, and maintenance.

Education

University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia

PHD IN SYSTEM AND INFORMATION ENGINEERING - ADVISOR: LAURA BARNES

August 2017 - Present

- Project: Conversational agent in mental health
- GPA: 3.98

Amirkabir University of Technology

Tehran, Iran

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE - ADVISOR: S. MEHDI HASHEMI

2011 - 2013

- · Thesis: Improve Patient's Satisfactions by using Electronic Medical Records and Building Management Systems (sensors)
- GPA: 18.26/20 (Thesis grade: 19.5/20)

Amirkabir University of Technology

Tehran, Iran

B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE - ADVISOR: S. MEHDI HASHEMI

2007 - 2011

- · Thesis: A New Urban Train Boarding/Alighting Strategy Proposition Using Passengers Micro-Movement Modeling
- GPA: 18/20 (Thesis grade: 20/20)

Experience _____

Graduate Research Assistant

August 2017 - PRESENT

University of Virginia

- · Digital Coaching: how to use a conversational agent to optimize utilization, compliance, efficacy, and maintenance of mental health program?
- EyeCar: Using eye-tracking data to determine drivers' state to give them right alarm.
- Managing Anxiety: how does cognitive behavior modification change the anxious person's behavior?
- Attrition: how to detect a participant is planning to leave the study at right time.
- Mental-health framework: how to detect loneliness of individual based on their text communication.
- MindTrail project: Data analysis for finding response and behavior pattern of users.
- · Emotion regulation: How anxious people regulate their emotion base on their location and their EMA response.

Researcher Sept 2015 - July 2017

KNOWLEDGE REPRESENTATION LAB - TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY

· ALM: creating a compiler for modular action language

Software Developer 2011 - 2014

ITS - AMIRKABIR UNIVERSITY OF TECHONOLGY

- · Business Intelligent: how to recommend the product to the user based on their history of orders
- Intelligent Parking: develop a system to show vacant spots in parking for reservation

Researcher 2011 - 2013

NORC - AMIRKABIR UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY

- Energy Management in Hospital: Resource allocation
- Decision Support System: dynamic resource allocation for assigning clinicians to patients

MARCH 1, 2020 SONIA BAEE · CURRICULUM VITAE



Teaching Assistant, Amirkabir University of Technology

Fall 2011

CS 1316104: PRINCIPLE OF COMPUTER 2

- Developed the assignments, final project and grade them
- · Held office hours

Teaching Assistant, Amirkabir University of Technology

Spring 2011

CS 1316004: PRINCIPLE OF COMPUTER 1

- Developed the assignments, final project and grade them
- · Held office hours

Co-Instructor, Amirkabir University of Technology

Spring 2012

CS 1316163: PRINCIPLE OF SOFTWARE DESIGN

- Developed some of the assignments, final project and grade them
- · Developed course instructions and course materials

Guest lecturer, Texas Tech University

Fall 2016

CS 2413: DATA STRUCTURE

Teaching different types of search algorithms

Publications_

SocialText: A Framework for Understanding the Relationship Between Digital

2019 Communication Patterns and Mental Health., Mendu, S., Boukhechba, M., Baglione, A., Baee, S., Wu, C., Barnes, L., 2019, January. In 2019 IEEE 13th International Conference on Semantic Computing (ICSC) (pp. 428-433). IEEE.

Web-based Interpretation Training for Anxiety: Testing Target Engagement and

2019 **Effectiveness for a Treatment Seeking Community Sample**, Ji, J.L., Baee, S., Zhang, D., Meyer, J., Barnes, L.E., Teachman, B., UNDER REVIEW

Do I really feel better? Effectiveness of emotion regulation strategies depends on the measure and social anxiety, Daniel, Katharine E and Baee, Sonia and Boukhechba, Mehdi and

Barnes, Laura E and Teachman, Bethany A, Depression and anxiety, 2019, Wiley Online Library What is effective? Assessing different aspects of emotion regulation effectiveness in daily

life., Daniel, K., Baee, S., Barnes, L.E., Teachman, B.,Regulating Emotions Effectively: New Approaches to Understanding Effects of Time, Person, and Development. Symposium to be presented at the Association for Psychological Science Annual Convention, Washington, D.C.

A social cognitive theory-based framework for monitoring medication adherence applied to endocrine therapy in breast cancer survivors., Boukhechba, M., Baee, S., Nobles, A.L.,

2018 Gong, J., Wells, K. and Barnes, L.E., 2018, March. In IEEE-EMBS International Conference on Biomedical and Health Informatics. IEEE-EMBS International Conference on Biomedical and Health Informatics (Vol. 2018, p. 275). NIH Public Access.

Passenger Boarding/Alighting Management in Urban Rail Transportation, Baee, Sonia,

2012 Eshghi, F., and Hashemi, S. M.,2012 JOINT RAIL CONFERENCEPhiladelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, April 17-19

Skills

2019

Programming Python, Java, R, C/C++, SQL programming

Web HTML, Angular. Js, Javascript, CSS

Research Interest

- Conversational agent
- Recommendation System
- Text Mining
- · Reinforcement Learning

- Mental Health
- · Mobile Sensing
- · Personal Health care Informatics
- Mathematics Modeling and Simulating

Honors & Awards

2019 Distinguished Graduate Student Award, University of Virginia 2018 NSF Travel Awards, IEEE - EMBS Distinguished Fellowship, one of the most prestigious fellowships offered to engineering 2017 students at the University of Virginia. Presidential Fellowship, this fellowship was funded in part by the Ed and Linda Whitacre 2016 Graduate Fellowship Endowment in Texas Tech University Scholarship Recipient, to attend CRA-W (Computing Research Association) Grad Cohort 2015 Workshop. Presidential Fellowship, this fellowship was funded in part by the Ed and Linda Whitacre 2015 Graduate Fellowship Endowment in Texas Tech University 2nd Place, among Computer Science - Artificial Intelligent M.S. students, Amirkabir University of 2013 2011 **Distinguished BSc student award**, with honorary acceptance for the MSc program 1st Place, among Computer Science and Mathematic B.S. students, Amirkabir University of 2010 Technology.

Service

- **REU mentor**, Creating personalized-content for anxious people in the study, University of 2019
- Academic and Industry Chair, Link Lab Student Committee on Culture and Livability, 2018-2019 University of Virginia
- 2018-2020 Grad SWE board, webmaster of Women Engineers organization, University of Virginia
- 2018 **REU mentor**, Detecting mental health from social media data, University of Virginia
- NSBE UVA recruiter, recruiting prospective students at the 2018 National Society of Black 2018 Engineers (NSBE) National Convention, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania
- 2018 **SWE UVA recruiter**, recruit at the 2018 SWE National Convention, Minneapolis, Minnesota
- REU, Declarative Approaches to Knowledge Intensive Applications, Texas Tech Department of 2016